Finding Aid for Edward V. Olencki Papers, 1946-1993
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Edward V. Olencki papers 1946-1993 1960-1983
Olencki, Edward V.
1 linear ft.
0485 Aa 2
Edward V. Olencki was a practicing architect and a professor at the University of Michigan College of Architecture and Urban Planning from 1949 to 1987. Prior to coming to Ann Arbor, Olencki worked as a designer and draftsman for prominent architect Mies van der Rohe while studying at the Illinois Institute of Technology.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This collection was donated by Mrs. Irene Olencki (Donor 9271 ) in November 2002.
The record group is open without restriction.
Edward Olencki attended the Illinois Institute of Technology (IIT.), where he earned a BS in architecture in 1944 and an MS in 1949. During his time at IIT, he worked as a draftsman and designer in the offices of famed architect, Mies van der Rohe in Chicago from 1943 to 1948. In 1948, Olencki left Chicago to take a position at the University of Michigan as an instructor. He was promoted to assistant professor in 1950, associate professor in 1953, and full professor in 1963. Olencki primarily taught courses on construction materials and methods, comprehensive architectural design, and furniture design. His research interests focused on modern church architecture, and he completed two sabbaticals in Europe studying this theme. During his time at Michigan Olencki also ran his own architectural firm, designing homes, churches, and commercial buildings.
In 2000 Olencki saluted his former mentor and employer, Mies van der Rohe, by donating a collection of over 200 of Mies van der Rohe's architectural drawings to the University of Michigan. These drawings were exhibited as "Mies in Michigan."
When he retired in 1987, Olencki was named Professor Emeritus of Architecture in honor of his years as an excellent and devoted teacher (See Proceedings of the Board of Regents, June 1987). Olencki died on March 14, 2002 at the age of 79.
This collection primarily reflects Olencki's work as a practicing architect, but also contains some materials related to his research interest in church design, and his association with Mies van der Rohe.
Subjects:
Olencki, Edward V.; Architecture--Designs and plans.; Architects--Michigan.; University of Michigan. College of Architecture and Urban Planning; University of Michigan--Faculty; Mies van der Rohe, Ludwig 1886-1969.; Eaton, Leonard K.; St Mary Stdent Parish (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Divine Savior Parish (Westland, Mich.); Church architecture.; Mies van der Rohe, Ludwig 1886-1969.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Olencki, Edward V.; Architecture.; Architects.; Church architecture.; Photographs.; Mies van der Rohe, Ludwig 1886-1969.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Illinois Institute of Technology, 1949-1950
  The series Illinois Institute of Technology, 1949-1950, consists of Olencki's 1949 Masters thesis paper on church design, including photographs of his church model.
  - Thesis Photos and Negatives, 1949 (Box 1)
    - Church Model (Box 1)
    - Church Elevation (Box 1)
  - Masters Thesis, "The Small Catholic Church: Problem and Proposed Solution," 1950
- Architectural Plans, 1946-1993
  The Architectural Plans, 1946-1993 series is the largest part of the collection and contains architectural drawings and blueprints, letters, and proposals. The series contains three files on Mies van der Rohe buildings (technology center at Illinois Institute of Technology, and Algonquin Apartments and Lakeview Apartments). The series is divided by type of structure: residential, commercial, church, or academic. Residential architecture includes the home built for fellow architecture professor Leonard K. Eaton. Church architecture includes an addition to St. Mary's Student Chapel In Ann Arbor, and Divine Savior Church in Westland.
  - Residential
    - Various Sketches of New House Plans, 1953 (Box 1)
    - Freedman Residence, Ann Arbor, MI, 1953 (Box 1)
    - Eaton Residence, Ann Arbor, MI, 1962 (Box 1)
    - Algonquin Apartments, Mies van der Rohe, Architect (Box 1)
    - Lakeview Apartments, Mies van der Rohe, Architect (Box 1)
    - Magee Residence, Isle of Capri, Florida, 1985 (Box 1)
    - Scott Residence Addition, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Amsters Residence Remodel, Ann Arbor, MI, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Commercial
    - Campbell Construction Company, Detroit, MI, 1953 (Box 1)
    - Gabriel Richard Center, Ann Arbor, MI, 1963 1979 (Box 1)
  - Churches
    - St. Mary's Student Chapel, Ann Arbor, MI, 1966 (Box 1)
    - Divine Savior Church, Westland, MI, 1976, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Academic
    - New Technology Center for the Illinois Institute of Technology, Chicago, Illinois, Mies van der Rohe, Architect, 1946
- Miscellaneous, ca. 1960-1971
  The Miscellaneous, ca. 1960-1971, series contains church sketches and furniture designs, notes and letters from Olencki's sabbaticals, and greeting cards from Mies van der Rohe.
  - Church Sketches and Ideas (Box 1)
  - Church Furniture Designs (Box 1)
  - Greeting Cards from Mies van der Rohe (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Sabbaticals
    - 1959-1960 (Box 1)
    - 1966
- Photographs, ca. 1940s-1070s
  The Photographs, ca. 1940s-1970s series contains photos of building exteriors from Olencki's time with Mies van der Rohe as well as photos of Taliesin, Frank Lloyd Wright's home and workspace in Spring Green, Wisconsin.
  - Building Exteriors from time at the offices of Mies van der Rohe (includes photographs of Olencki with Mies) (Box 1)
  - Taliesin (by Frank Lloyd Wright) and exterior photos of Frank Lloyd Wright-designed office building (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous and unidentified photographs (Box 1)